You see, here we are in the seminar and we are all Sahaja Yogis and we are having a good
Jesteśmy tutaj na seminarium, wszyscy jesteśmy Sahaja yoginami i wszyscy dobrze się bawimy,
time, we are cracking jokes, we’re discussing things, etc., etc.
żartujemy, dyskutujemy, itp. To wszystko jest w porządku, mam na myśli,
But, this is all very well, I mean, one can enjoy oneself, in fact one should enjoy oneself
że można cieszyć się sobą, faktycznie powinniśmy się sobą cieszyć,
because the whole creation has been created in such a way that we should enjoy ourselves.
ponieważ całe stworzenie zostało utworzone w taki sposób, aby się sobą cieszyć.
From the dawn of the creation, the Shri Adi Shakti of the Universe has played out a drama
Od początku stworzenia Shri Adi Shakti Wszechświata odgrywała spektakl
using Her Deities, using all the powers that She created, to create a Universe so beautiful
używając Jej Bóstw, używając wszystkich mocy, które stworzyła do tworzenia tak pięknego Wszechświata,
that it should be possible for us to live in it in complete joy and complete enjoyment
który umożliwia nam życie w całkowitej radości i odczuwanie pełnej przyjemności
of our existence.
z naszego istnienia.
If one gives you an example…
Weźmy taki przykład…
Yesterday we sat and we listened to ragas.
Wczoraj siedzieliśmy i słuchaliśmy rag.
These ragas themselves were inspired by the Shri Adi Shakti in realized souls those who
Te ragi zostały zainspirowane przez Shri Adi Shakti w Zrealizowanych Duszach tych,
gave them to the world.
którzy dali je światu.
The whole thing has been created by Her in different aspects.
Całość została przez Nią stworzona w różnych aspektach,
So that we should enjoy ourselves and so that we should not be miserable.
abyśmy się cieszyli i nie byli nieszczęśliwi. A dlaczego Ona chce,
And why does She want us to be happy?
abyśmy byli szczęśliwi?
Because it is when you are happy and relaxed than the power of God can work on you, to
Dlatego, że jeżeli jesteście szczęśliwi i zrelaksowani, wtedy moc Boga może w was pracować,
raise you to a great height for which you are destined.
aby wznieść was na wielką wysokość, do której zostaliście przeznaczeni.
You see, this whole drama that has taken place is not a drama without purpose.
Ten cały spektakl, który ma nadal miejsce, nie jest spektaklem bez celu.
Within it lies something that is profoundly important and that something which is profoundly
Wewnątrz niego leży coś, co jest niezwykle ważne, i to co jest niezwykle
important is the awareness of God the Absolute the Almighty.
ważne, jest świadomością Boga, Absolutu, Wszechmogącego.
And this is the whole purpose of Sahaja Yoga.
I to jest cały cel Sahaja Yogi.
All the different techniques we use are a bridge to this.
Różne techniki, których używamy są do tego pomostem.
You see, you have to understand what is Shri Mataji on this Earth.
Musicie zrozumieć kim jest Shri Mataji na tej Ziemi.
She is the Adi Shakti.
Ona jest Shri Adi Shakti.
Now, how many people know what is the Adi Shakti?
Teraz, ilu ludzi wie, kim jest Shri Adi Shakti?
The Adi Shakti is the power of God Almighty Himself.
Adi Shakti jest mocą Boga Wszechmogącego.
It is the highest manifest thing in the Universe.
To jest najbardziej oczywista rzecz we Wszechświecie.
When this thing takes Avatara in the Universe for the first time, there must be a profound
Kiedy Ona po raz pierwszy przybiera formę avatara we Wszechświecie, musi się za tym
significance behind this.
kryć głębokie znaczenie.
And this profound significance must be the awareness of the Lord the Almighty.
I to głębokie znaczenie musi być świadomością Pana Wszechmogącego.
In your body are placed the various chakras of the tantra.
W waszym ciele umieszczone są różne czakry tantry.
The instrument.
Narzędzie.
Tantra means instrument.
Tantra oznacza narzędzie.
What are this chakras for?
Po co są te czakry?
And people spend a lot of time cleaning them, taking them out, putting them in salt water,
I ludzie spędzają dużo czasu na czyszczeniu ich, wyjmowaniu, wkładaniu ich do wody z solą, ponownym
putting them back again.
wkładaniu ich na miejsce.
But for what purpose?
Ale w jakim celu? Widzicie, musicie
You see, you have to think for what purpose.
zastanowić się, w jakim celu.
Try to think why you are here instead of doing things routinely.
Spróbujcie pomyśleć, dlaczego tu jesteście, zamiast wykonywać rzeczy rutynowo.
The chakras raise the awareness of the human individual from step to step, higher and higher
Czakry podnoszą świadomość jednostki ludzkiej krok po kroku, coraz wyżej i wyżej,
until it can reach the throne of the Almighty Himself.
aż dotrze ona do tronu samego Wszechmogącego.
That is their purpose.
To jest ich cel.
So, those who do not use it for that are like a man who has a Rolls Royce who takes it apart,
Więc ci, którzy ich nie używają do tego celu są jak człowiek, który posiada Rolls Royce’a,
puts it in oil, puts it together again, starts the engine and goes nowhere.
rozbiera go na części, oliwi, składa części ponownie, uruchamia silnik, ale nigdzie nie jedzie.
You see, the whole tantras have been given to you to raise your attention to the Absolutely
Widzicie, że wszystkie tantry zostały wam dane, aby podnieść waszą uwagę do Absolutu,
the Almighty.
Wszechmogącego.
The whole of Sahaja Yoga has been given to you to raise your attention to the Absolute
Cała Sahaja Yoga została wam dana, aby podnieść waszą uwagę do Absolutu,
Your friends are given to you for this purpose.
Wasi przyjaciele są wam dani do tego celu.
And the Shri Adi Shakti Herself has appeared before you to give you this.
A Shri Adi Shakti osobiście pojawiła się przed wami, aby wam to umożliwić.
Now, there is no doubt that Shri Adi Shakti is Mahamaya.
Nie ma wątpliwości, że Shri Adi Shakti jest Mahamayą.
What does Mahamaya mean?
Co oznacza Mahamaya?
And why is She Mahamaya?
I dlaczego Ona jest Mahamayą? Widzicie, powinniście pytać
You see, you should question these basic fundamentals.
o te podstawowe zasady.
After all, God is the Prime Architect of the Universe.
Ostatecznie Bóg jest Głównym Architektem Wszechświata.
There is nothing that He does that is purposeless.
Nie ma niczego co On robi, a co jest
You have to understand this.
pozbawione sensu. Musicie to zrozumieć.
If we have purpose in what we do in our limitations how much greater is His purpose?
Jeśli my mamy cel w tym co robimy przy naszych ograniczeniach, jak o wiele większy jest Jego cel?
You see, if a long time ago, more than 1,400 years ago, Shri Adi Shankaracharya told human
Dawno temu, ponad 1400 lat temu, Shri Adi Shankaracharya powiedział istotom ludzkim,
beings, “You are the Absolute, there is no difference between you and God the Almighty,
że "jesteście Absolutem, nie ma różnicy pomiędzy wami a Bogiem Wszechmogącym, Advaita".
Now, if you are the Absolute, the Atma unless you are diluted, there can be no creation,
Otóż, jeżeli jesteście Absolutem, Atmą, chyba że jesteście osłabieni, to nie może być żadnego tworzenia, prawda?
Because if you are always aware that you’re the Atma Tattwa, how can you be involved in
Ponieważ jeśli jesteście zawsze świadomi, że jesteście Atma Tattwą, jak możecie być zaangażowani w tworzenie?
You’ll always be lost in meditation on your own existence.
Zawsze będziecie zagubieni w medytacji nad własnym życiem.
You have to understand this basic fact.
Musicie zrozumieć ten podstawowy fakt.
So, the Mahamaya was necessary for the creation.
Tak więc Mahamaya była niezbędna do tworzenia.
She was necessary for the evolution of the creation.
Była niezbędna do ewolucji tworzenia.
Because by playing out dramas for you she evolves you.
Ponieważ rozgrywając dla was spektakle, Ona was rozwija. I dopiero wtedy,
And it’s only when you reach a certain level that She can liberate you from herself.
kiedy osiągniecie pewien poziom Ona może was od Siebie uwolnić.
So, that you see beyond the Maya, the Absolute.
Tak, że widzicie poza Mayą, Absolutem.
Now, there is a saying in one of the Puranas that, “The Devi can only be worshiped by
W jednej z Puran jest powiedziane, że "Devi może być czczona tylko przez tych,
those who are both, intelligent and brave."
którzy są zarówno inteligentni jak i odważni".
And She cannot be worshiped by the stupid and the cowardly.
I nie może być czczona przez głupców i tchórzy.
This is very important, you see, we have been given brains.
To bardzo ważne, dostaliśmy umysły.
We haven’t been given brains to sort out trivialities of life.
Nie dostaliśmy umysłów, aby porządkować banały życia.
We have been given brains to chart our course to the Almighty the Absolute.
Dostaliśmy umysły, aby wytyczyć naszą drogę ku Wszechmogącemu, Absolutowi.
She is not going to spoon-feed you.
Ona nie ma zamiaru prowadzić was za rękę.
Beyond a certain point you have to find the course for yourself.
W pewnym momencie musicie wytyczyć dla siebie kierunek. Powodem tego jest to,
The reason for this is that unless you do so you are not worthy to be presented before
że jeśli tego nie uczynicie, nie jesteście godni, aby was zaprezentować przed Wszechmogącym.
Only those who are using their courage and their intelligence, the strength of their
Tylko ci, którzy używają swojej odwagi i inteligencji, siły swego
desire can find the course, are worthy really to come before Him.
pragnienia mogą odnaleźć kierunek, są naprawdę godni, aby przed Nim stanąć.
This is all part of the evolution of mankind.
To wszystko jest częścią ewolucji ludzkości.
To understand and appreciate the Almighty you have to have an awareness that is capable
Aby zrozumieć i docenić Wszechmogącego, musicie mieć świadomość, która jest w stanie Go przyjąć.
About two years ago Shri Mataji came to Riyadh and I’ve written a Sanskrit poem which I
Około dwóch lat temu Shri Mataji przybyła do Rijadu a ja napisałem wiersz sanskrycki,
presented to Her.
który Jej ofiarowałem.
And She began to complete it for me because it was incomplete.
I Ona zaczęła go dla mnie uzupełniać, ponieważ nie był skończony.
And one of the verses was, “…how can I pour all this into such small cups?
A jeden z wersetów brzmiał: "…Jak mogę przelać to wszystko do tak małych pucharów?…"
You see, because the awareness, the brain is not yet developed to the point it can take
Ponieważ świadomość, umysł nie jest jeszcze rozwinięty do tego stopnia,
the radiation, the full weight of radiation of the Almighty into it.
aby przyjąć promieniowanie, pełny ciężar promieniowania Wszechmogącego.
So, how are you going to develop the brain?
Jak więc macie zamiar rozwinąć umysł?
After all, the brain is the Agnya chakra.
Przede wszystkim, umysł jest czakrą Agnya.
You develop the brain by focusing it on the nature of the Almighty the Absolute.
Rozwijacie umysł skupiając się na naturze Wszechmogącego, Absolutu.
Contemplating it every day of one’s existence.
Kontemplując Go każdego dnia swojego istnienia.
In this way the attention goes up to it.
W ten sposób uwaga wznosi się do Niego. A nerwy w mózgu stają się
And the nerves in the brain get refined.
bardziej wyrafinowane.
The petals of the Sahastrara get refined to the point that they can receive the grace
Płatki Sahastrary stają się bardziej subtelne do tego stopnia, że mogą otrzymać łaskę
of the Absolute and His awareness.
Absolutu i Jego świadomości.
The Shri Adi Shakti is His Shakti.
Shri Adi Shakti jest Jego Shakti.
She is the power by which all things are done.
Jest mocą, dzięki której wszystko się dokonuje.
She is the one who refine your brain for you.
Ona jest Tą, która dla was udoskonala wasz umysł.
But you yourself have to put your attention there.
Ale wy sami musicie zwrócić na to uwagę.
It is very easy in Sahaja Yoga because one is left alone a lot to put one’s attention
W Sahaja Yodze jest bardzo łatwo, ponieważ często pozostaje się samemu, aby móc dostrzec banały.
A chakra may catch.
Czakra może blokować się.
But what does it matter?
Ale co to za różnica?
The catch may release within five or ten minutes.
Blokada może puścić w ciągu pięciu lub dziesięciu minut.
So, why bother about it?
Więc po co się tym przejmować?
That we know that the catches move from chakra to chakra.
Wiemy o tym, że blokady przenoszą się z czakry do czakry.
That the movement of the kundalini moves from chakra to chakra.
Że ruch Kundalini przesuwa się z czakry do czakry.
So, what is the purpose of concentrating on things that are trivial?
Więc jaki jest cel koncentrowania się na rzeczach, które są nieistotne? W przeszłości,
In the past, you see, many great seekers came on this Earth to seek God.
jak widzicie, wielu wielkich poszukiwaczy przybyło na tę Ziemię, aby szukać Boga. Więc czego
After what are you seeking?
jeszcze szukacie?
What does seeking mean?
Co oznacza szukanie?
It means to seek God.
To oznacza szukanie Boga.
They had no Shri Adi Shakti to help them.
Oni nie mieli Shri Adi Shakti, aby im pomóc.
You have it here in front of you.
Wy macie Ją tutaj przed sobą.
So, you should take advantage of it.
Więc powinniście z tego skorzystać.
And try and become fixed at that point which is the Absolute.
I postarajcie się ustabilizować w tym punkcie, który jest Absolutem.
And you may all be here in a collective but the relationship between you and the Absolute
I wszyscy możecie przebywać tutaj w kolektywie, ale relacja między wami i Absolutem
has to be individual between you and Him alone.
musi by indywidualna, między wami i Nim samym.
And when you see Him, you don’t see anyone else.
A kiedy Go zobaczycie, nie będziecie widzieć nikogo innego.
You see.
Widzicie.
It is very good to be in the collective, it is very good to be with each other to enjoy
Dobrze jest być w kolektywie, bardzo dobrze jest przebywać ze sobą, aby cieszyć się
each other’s company but your relationship with each other should be such that it fosters
swoim towarzystwem, ale wasze wzajemne relacje powinny sprzyjać
that ascent to the Divine the Absolute.
wznoszeniu się do Boskiego Absolutu.
We have to be very clear.
Musicie to zrozumieć.
The whole purpose of Sahaja Yoga is this ascent.
Całkowitym celem Sahaja Yogi jest ten wzrost.
The great Goddess Herself the Shri Adi Shakti has a devotion to our Lord which is indescribable
Wielka Bogini, sama Shri Adi Shakti przejawia oddanie dla naszego Pana, które jest nie do opisania na poziomie ludzkim.
The whole play between the Almighty and the Shakti is something which is one of the profoundest
Cała gra pomiędzy Wszechmogącym a Shakti jest czymś, co jest jedną
mysteries of mankind and of the Creation.
z najgłębszych tajemnic ludzkości i Stworzenia.
And the deepest desire of the Shri Adi Shakti is the ascent of Her creation and Her children
A najgłębszym pragnieniem Shri Adi Shakti jest wstąpienie Jej Tworzenia i Jej dzieci
to the throne of the Almighty as an offering to Her Lord.
na tron Wszechmocnego, jako dar dla Jej Pana.
Just as we, when we present an offering to Shri Mataji if there are flowers, we take
Podobnie jak my, kiedy ofiarowujemy dary dla Shri Mataji, jeśli to są kwiaty, usuwamy
out the worst flowers, we present only the best, the most perfect.
najgorsze kwiaty, ofiarowujemy tylko najlepsze, najdoskonalsze.
So, when the Shri Adi Shakti offers to Her Lord Her Creation it is something at a level
Tak więc, kiedy Shri Adi Shakti ofiarowuje Panu Jej dzieło, jest to coś na poziomie
far removed from this.
dalekim od tego.
And only the most perfect that can be presented before Him.
I tylko to najdoskonalsze może być Jemu zaprezentowane.
You see.
Widzicie.
You have to understand this.
Musicie to zrozumieć.
As human beings we have no importance.
Jako istoty ludzkie,
Except, in so far as we play a part in this play between the Lord and His Shakti.
nie mamy znaczenia, z wyjątkiem tego, na ile odgrywamy rolę w tej grze pomiędzy Panem a Jego Shakti.
The entire creation can be discarded, if it does not serve this purpose.
Całe tworzenie można odrzucić, jeżeli nie służy ono temu celowi.
Cause there are only two things which are real in the Universe and that is the Lord
Ponieważ jest tylko ich dwoje, którzy są istotni we Wszechświecie, jest to Pan
and His Shakti.
i Jego Shakti.
All else is superfluous to this and of no importance.
Wszystko inne jest zbędne i bez znaczenia.
At the end of creation only those two things will remain.
Pod koniec tworzenia pozostaną tylko Oni we dwoje.
So, you must not take lightly what is happening.
Więc nie wolno wam lekceważyć tego, co się dzieje. Jesteście istotnymi
You are the essential parts and pieces of this drama.
częściami tego spektaklu, tego bardzo głębokiego dramatu,
This very profound drama which is the basis and the internal root of the Universe.
który jest podstawą i wewnętrznym korzeniem Wszechświata.
Have you ever considered why the Mooladhara chakra has four petals?
Czy zastanawialiście się kiedyś, dlaczego czakra Mooladhara ma cztery płatki?
What does it mean?
Co to znaczy?
Why four?
Dlaczego cztery?
It is four because if you combine the Lord and the Shakti in the Sushumna where Their
Jest ich cztery, ponieważ jeżeli połączycie Pana i Shakti w Sushumnie, gdzie Ich stopy się opierają,
feet rest you will find four feet resting.
znajdziecie tam cztery spoczywające stopy.
It is the… that is why it is the ultimate purity because it represents the combined
Jest to… to dlatego to jest najwyższa czystość, ponieważ reprezentuje ona połączone
feet of the Lord and his Shakti and that is given as a throne to the son, Ganesha, the
stopy Pana i Jego Shakti, i ona jest dana jako tron dla syna, Ganeshy,
Lord, the Omkara to sit on.
Pana, Omkary, aby na nim zasiadł.
These things are very important, very profound.
Te rzeczy są bardzo ważne, bardzo głębokie.
To be the seat of the play of the Lord and Shakti one needs extreme purity, extreme wisdom
Aby być siedzibą gry Pana i Shakti potrzebna jest skrajna czystość, skrajna mądrość
and extreme awareness of what is happening.
i skrajna świadomość tego, co się dzieje.
The whole purpose of this creation is that and that alone.
Cały cel tego tworzenia jest tym i tylko tym.
The creation was not made for you to iron saris.
Tworzenie nie zostało przeznaczone do prasowania sari.
To worry about your dhobi [laundryman].
Ani do martwienia się o dhobi [praczki].
These are totally irrelevant.
Są one całkowicie nieistotne.
They won’t even last a century, leave alone eternity.
Nie przetrwają nawet stulecia, opuszczą samotnie wieczność.
Nor is organization there.
Nie ma tam też organizacji.
You can organize till you’re blue in the face but unless the desire of the Absolute
Możecie organizować do utraty tchu, ale jeśli nie działa
works you will not get another Sahaja Yogi.
pragnienie Absolutu, nie otrzymacie kolejnego Sahaja yogina.
You have seen this.
Widzieliście to.
Many of you have.
Wielu z was widziało.
We had many wonderful experiences in the early days when we turned up at empty halls in spite
Mieliśmy wiele wspaniałych doświadczeń wcześniej, kiedy pojawialiśmy się w pustych salach
of massive publicity.
pomimo
You see, you do not do anything.
ogromnego rozgłosu. Widzicie, wy nic nie robicie.
Lord Krishna when He came He said, “You do not do anything.
Pan Krishna, kiedy przyszedł, powiedział: "Ty nic nie robisz.
I do it all."
Ja robię to wszystko".
So, the human being who deludes himself into thinking he is doing.
Tak więc istota ludzka zwodzi samą siebie na myślenie o tym, że ona coś robi.
He is not doing.
Ona nic nie robi.
He said, “Act!
[Shri Krishna]
You have to act.
powiedział: "Działaj! Musisz działać.
But leave the results of your actions to Me."
Ale pozostaw Mi rezultaty swoich działań".
So, act without expectation is what He is saying.
Więc działanie bez oczekiwań, jest tym, o czym On mówi.
Now, how are you going to awaken?
Teraz, jak macie zamiar się obudzić?
What you are going to do?
Co zamierzacie zrobić?
You see, when one acts, everyone knows what the left side is what the right side is.
Kiedy się działa, każdy wie, co jest lewą stroną, co jest prawą stroną.
One acts by the right using the power of desire of the left.
Działamy poprzez prawą stronę używając siły pragnienia lewej strony.
This is something that is well known to everybody.
Jest to coś, co jest wszystkim dobrze znane.
Through which chakra does one act?
Za pomocą której czakry się działa? Która jest
Which is the chakra of activity?
czakrą aktywności?
Who will answer it?
Kto na to odpowie?
Of creation?
Czakrą tworzenia?
You must all know this, it’s basic stuff.
Wszyscy musicie to wiedzieć, to podstawowe rzeczy.
The Swadhisthana.
Swadhisthana.
Ok.
W porządku.
The Swadhisthana is on the right, is it not?
Swadhisthana jest po prawej stronie, prawda?
And the Shuddha Ichha is on the left.
A Shuddha Ichha jest po lewej.
So, what is the bridge between the desire of God the Almighty and action?
A więc, co jest pomostem między pragnieniem Boga Wszechmogącego a działaniem?
It is the left Swadhisthana chakra.
Jest nim lewa czakra Swadhisthana.
Correct?
Zgadza się?
And that is why all boots go and sit there.
I dlatego wszystkie buce tam idą i osiadają.
To disconnect your action from your desire.
Aby odłączyć wasze działanie od waszego pragnienia.
Very simple, you see.
Bardzo proste, widzicie.
Wherever the boots hit hard you must know that is an important chakra.
Gdziekolwiek buce uderzają mocno, musicie wiedzieć, że to jest ważna czakra.
Now, you see, although we are human beings, we are by the grace of God enlightened souls.
Teraz widzicie, że chociaż jesteśmy istotami ludzkimi, jesteśmy dzięki łasce Boga, Oświeconymi Duszami.
This means that the entire tantra of the Universe is present in miniature within us.
Oznacza to, że cała tantra Wszechświata jest obecna w nas w miniaturze.
This Shri Mataji has done and She said, “I’ve placed you there.
To uczyniła Shri Mataji i powiedziała: "Ja was tam umieściłam.
Now, what you do with yourself is your affair."
Teraz to, co zrobicie ze sobą to wasza sprawa".
Now, as the Shuddha Ichha of the Universe … Does everyone know what the Shuddha Ichha
Teraz jako Shuddha Ichha Wszechświata… Czy wszyscy wiedzą, czym jest Shuddha Ichha?
The Shuddha Ichha is the pure desire of the Universe.
Shuddha Ichha jest czystym pragnieniem Wszechświata.
Now, what is the pure desire of the Universe?
A jakie jest czyste pragnienie Wszechświata?
The pure desire of the Universe is God, the desire of God Almighty Himself.
Czystym pragnieniem Wszechświata jest Bóg, pragnienie samego Boga Wszechmogącego.
As this flows through the Ida nadi of the Universe and is carried by the Goddess Shri
Jako że ono przepływa przez Ida Nadi Wszechświata i jest przenoszone przez Boginię
Mahakali to be placed, deposited within the kundalini.
Shri Mahakali, aby być umieszczone, zdeponowane w Kundalini.
So, this flows within your left side or can flow within your left side if you desire it.
Więc ono przepływa po waszej lewej stronie lub może płynąć po waszej lewej stronie, jeżeli tego chcecie.
To inform your activities.
Aby poinformować wasze działania.
Now, you see, unless you are connected your activities are without meaning.
Dopóki nie jesteście połączeni, wasze działania nie mają znaczenia.
It is like ants scurrying around not knowing what they are doing.
Jak w przypadku mrówek, które biegając dookoła, nie wiedzą co robią.
So, first, one has to establish within oneself the pure desire.
Tak więc najpierw trzeba ustanowić w sobie czyste pragnienie.
Let it flow within your Ida nadi.
Pozwólcie mu płynąć w waszej Ida Nadi.
How would you do that?
Jak to zrobicie?
It’s very simple.
To jest bardzo proste.
You pray to Shri Mataji and you say, “You are the Shuddha Ichha of the Universe and
Modlicie się do Shri Mataji i mówicie: "Ty jesteś Shuddha Ichha Wszechświata
I worship You as such."
i ja wielbię Cię taką". Jeśli tylko to zrobicie,
If you just do that, pray to Her, pray to Her, is this, She will flow with such force
pomodlicie się do Niej, pomodlicie się do Niej, to Ona będzie płynęła z taką siłą
within your Ida nadis that She will break anything that is in your left Swadhisthana
w waszych Ida Nadi, że zniszczy wszystko, co jest w waszym lewym Swadhisthanie
and flow into the right.
i popłynie na prawo.
To inform your activity.
Aby poinformować wasze działanie.
You cannot catch on the right side if your left side is strong.
Nie możecie mieć blokad po prawej stronie, jeśli wasza lewa strona jest silna.
You see.
Widzicie.
So, that is the first stage.
Więc to jest pierwszy etap.
If you do that the Shuddha Ichha, you don’t need to do more than this, the Shuddha Ichha
Jeżeli to zrobicie to Shuddha Ichha… nie musicie robić nic więcej, Shuddha Ichha
will flow through all your chakras, it will eventually break open the barriers that are
będzie płynąć przez wszystkie wasze czakry, ostatecznie przełamie bariery, w waszym mózgu.
in your brain and infuse with enlightenment and nectar every nerve fiber and cell within
które są w waszym umyśle i napełni oświeceniem i nektarem każde włókno nerwowe i każdą komórkę w waszym mózgu.
As it does that your whole consciousness and awareness will be altered.
Kiedy to się stanie, to zmieni się cała wasza przytomność umysłu i świadomość.
As it is altered your awareness will be filled with the awareness of the Absolute.
Kiedy one się zmienią to wasza świadomość zostanie napełniona świadomością Absolutu.
As it is filled with the awareness of the Absolute you will see Shri Mataji clearly
Kiedy ona zostanie napełniona świadomością Absolutu ujrzycie wyraźnie
for what She is which is the Shakti of God Almighty Himself.
Shri Mataji, kim Ona jest, że jest Shakti samego Boga Wszechmogącego.
We will not say, “Shri Mataji did this, Shri Mataji did that,” you know, all the
Nie powiemy: "Shri Mataji zrobiła to, Shri Mataji zrobiła tamto”, znacie całą tę Mayę
Maya and the play.
i grę. Niektórzy ludzie
Some people fill tragic one minute, happy next…
czują się przez moment tragicznie, a za chwilę są szczęśliwi…
This is all nonsense.
To wszystko nie ma sensu.
If you are based in yourself you will remain absolutely stable in the sight of your parents,
Jeśli polegacie na sobie pozostaniecie całkowicie stabilni w zasięgu wzroku waszych Rodziców,
in the sight of the Almighty.
w zasięgu wzroku Wszechmogącego.
You do not shift from day to day.
Nie zmieniacie się z dnia na dzień.
You don’t doubt yourself.
Nie wątpicie w siebie.
You cannot become Nirvikalpa until you know this.
Nie możecie stać się Nirvikalpa, dopóki się o tym nie dowiecie.
Because part of the Nirvikalpa is not just doubting God or Shri Mataji.
Ponieważ częścią Nirvikalpy nie jest tylko wątpienie w Boga lub Shri Mataji.
It’s very easy not to do that.
Bardzo łatwo tego nie robić.
It’s not doubting yourself as an extension of Them.
To jest niewątpienie w samego siebie jako Ich przedłużenie.
Because as Shri Mataji said, She has made every single one of us into a part of Her
Ponieważ, jak powiedziała Shri Mataji, Ona sprawiła, że każdy z nas stał się częścią Jej ciała.
So, to doubt oneself is in a sense to doubt Her.
Tak więc, wątpić w samego siebie, to w pewnym sensie wątpić w Nią.
Now, people try to avoid recognizing what has been done to them by getting Realization
Teraz ludzie starają się unikać rozpoznania, co zostało dla nich zrobione przez otrzymanie Realizacji
in Sahaja Yoga.
w Sahaja Yodze. Nie chcecie dostrzec, że oni zostali
You don’t want to see that they have been made a part of the body of God Almighty Himself
uczynieni częścią ciała samego Boga Wszechmogącego
in a sense of His Shakti.
w znaczeniu Jego Shakti.
Because this means that you can’t behave in the same old ways you used to behave.
Ponieważ oznacza to, że nie możecie zachowywać się w taki sam stary sposób, w jaki zwykle zachowywaliście się.
You can’t be attached to the same old things which you used to be attached to.
Nie możecie być przywiązani do tych samych starych rzeczy, do których kiedyś byliście przywiązani.
You have to change, you see.
Musicie to zmienić.
Ready?
Gotowi?
Ok.
Ok.
And this is something that people don’t understand.
I to jest coś, czego ludzie nie rozumieją.
And this is an avoidance of Sahaja Yoga, this is running away from it.
I to jest unikanie Sahaja Yogi, to jest ucieczka od niej.
The essence of Sahaja Yoga is the fact that people have been …, human being has been
Istotą Sahaja Yogi jest fakt, że ludzie zostali… ludzie zostali wzięci,
taken, they have been given realization, they have been made part of the body of the Divine
dostąpili Realiazcji, zostali częścią ciała Bogini
and they have been given the opportunity to raise their awareness to the highest level
i otrzymali możliwość podniesienia swojej świadomości na najwyższy poziom,
to attain God realization.
aby osiągnąć
That is it.
Realizację Boga. To jest to.
It’s very simple.
To jest bardzo proste.
Everything else is a waste of time.
Wszystko inne to strata czasu. I trzeba uznać,
And one has to recognize that although we may be Sahaja Yogis we do not run the Universe;
że chociaż możemy być Sahaja yoginami, to nie zarządzamy Wszechświatem;
the Universe is run by us.
Wszechświat jest zarządzany przez nas.
I mean, run for us by the Almighty.
Mam na myśli, jest zarządzany dla nas przez Wszechmogącego.
And run by us for the Almighty.
I kierowany przez nas dla Wszechmogącego. Nie możemy zdecydować,
We cannot decide this has to happen, this has to happen, we have to have twenty people
że tak się stanie, to musi się stać, musimy mieć dwadzieścia osób w przyszłym tygodniu.
Cannot happen.
To nie może się zdarzyć.
God decides how many people He wants, He decides where and when, you just have to be instruments.
Bóg decyduje, ilu ludzi chce, decyduje, gdzie i kiedy, po prostu musicie być narzędziami.
Not one of us can change the Universe even so much.
Nikt z nas nie może nawet o tyle zmienić Wszechświata.
Unless we do it in the… on the crest of a wave which precedes from the Almighty and
Dopóki nie zrobimy tego… na grzbiecie fali, która poprzedza Wszechmogącego i dopóki
work as instruments.
nie działamy jak narzędzia.
The old days of siddhic Yogis who ride on clouds and transform mountains and hurl thunderbolts
Dawne dni yoginów siddhi, którzy jeżdżą na chmurach, przemieniają góry i ciskają piorunami
are over, you see.
skończyły się. To było
That was meant for people who are right sided.
przeznaczone dla osób prawostronnych.
Who wanted to do things themselves.
Dla tego, kto chciał sam robić rzeczy.
That is not us.
To nie my.
We are parts of the body of the Goddess.
Jesteśmy częścią ciała Bogini.
And each one of us has to be like e nerve cell.
I każdy z nas musi być jak komórka nerwowa.
When the brain tells us what to do, we have to do it.
Kiedy mózg mówi nam co robić, musimy to zrobić.
As such we are all collective.
Jako tacy wszyscy jesteśmy kolektywni. To jest prawdziwa
That is the true collectivity.
kolektywność.
And if we… each of us recognize that we are a nerve cell in the brain of the Goddess,
I jeśli my, każdy z nas rozpozna, że jest komórką nerwową w mózgu Bogini,
permeating Her whole being then the whole boundaries between nationalities, and this
przenikając Jej całą istotę, potem całe granice między narodowościami i to, co utrzymuje
and that which keeps Sahaja Yogis apart dissolves.
Sahaja yoginów osobno, rozpuści się.
We all realize we are one, we are the same, that each one of us is individual and each
Wszyscy zdajemy sobie sprawę, że jesteśmy jednością, jesteśmy tacy sami, że każdy
one of us has an individual relationship to the Almighty.
z nas jest indywidualny i każdy z nas ma indywidualną relację
And all sorts of misidentifications fall away.
z Wszechmogącym, wszystkie rodzaje błędnych identyfikacji znikają.
Now one speaks a common language, no doubt about it, it is real.
Teraz mówimy wspólnym językiem, bez wątpienia, to jest prawdziwe. I to jest wspólny
And this is the common language of vibrations.
język wibracji.
If you are there you do not know how but you communicate with people who have a different
Jeżeli gdzieś jesteście, nie wiecie jak, ale komunikujecie się z ludźmi, którzy mówią odrębnym językiem.
It’s so simple really.
To naprawdę proste.
So, I wish really in this lecture to make you aware of what is been given in Sahaja
Tak więc naprawdę chciałbym, abyście uświadomili sobie poprzez ten wykład, co zostało dane w Sahaja Yodze.
What has been done by the Great Goddess in Her absolute nature and for what purpose.
Co zrobiła Wielka Bogini w Jej absolutnej naturze i w jakim celu.
So that you do not waste neither time nor energy on other things.
Abyście nie tracili ani czasu ani energii na inne rzeczy.
There is nothing greater than this.
Nie ma nic większego niż to.
And since the Goddess Herself is All Powerful, beyond time, beyond everything.
A ponieważ sama Bogini jest Wszechpotężna, poza czasem, poza wszystkim.
So, your awareness has to be of a nature that can comprehend that and be one with that awareness.
Tak więc wasza świadomość musi być takiej natury, która może to zrozumieć, i która jest jednością z tą świadomością.
You can become one with Her in awareness, no doubt.
Bez wątpienia możecie stać się jednością z Nią w świadomości.
And see things as She sees things.
I widzieć rzeczy tak, jak Ona je postrzega.
But for this your brain has to develop, you see.
Ale do tego wasz umysł musi się rozwinąć.
So, this is what one has to do.
Więc to jest to, co trzeba zrobić.
And really the rest of it is not important.
I naprawdę reszta nie jest ważna.
At that level, it doesn’t matter how time passes.
Na tym poziomie nie ma znaczenia, jak upływa czas.
At that level, it doesn’t matter whether there are miracles or not because the whole
Na tym poziomie nie ma znaczenia, czy istnieją cuda czy nie, ponieważ cała
concept of a miracle is non-existent.
koncepcja cudu nie istnieje.
Everything follows the desire of the Absolute.
Wszystko podąża za pragnieniem Absolutu.
Who makes the rules that arbitrates between a miracle and a non-miracle?
Kto tworzy reguły rozstrzygające co jest cudem, a co nie?
Humans beings.
Istoty ludzkie.
It’s not God.
Nie Bóg.
For God there is no such things as a miracle.
Dla Boga nie istnieje coś takiego jak cud.
Everything is possible to Him.
Wszystko jest dla Niego możliwe.
So, what I’m saying is hitch your awareness higher, hook it at the higher level, keep
Więc to o czym mówię: unieście waszą świadomość wyżej, uczepcie ją na wyższym poziomie, zatrzymajcie ją tam.
So that you see really what is happening.
Tak, że zobaczycie, co naprawdę się dzieje.
And do not, in spite of everything that has been given, continue to move in the same circles,
I nie starajcie się, pomimo wszystkiego co zostało dane, kontynuować poruszania się w tych samych kręgach,
low circles that one inhabited before one’s realization.
niskich kręgach, w których się przebywało przed Realizacją.
This is very important.
To jest bardzo ważne.
This is so important that I don’t know how to say it.
Jest to tak ważne, że nie wiem, jak to powiedzieć.
Work to increase the structure and capacity of one’s brain, so that you can comprehend
Pracujcie nad zwiększeniem struktury i pojemności umysłu tak, że będziecie mogli pojąć to,
that which is Absolute.
co jest Absolutem.
I do not know if there is anything more to say to this.
Nie wiem, czy jest coś więcej do powiedzenia.
I remember once a long time back when I first met Shri Mataji, Gregoire was there, lots
Pamiętam, że dawno temu, kiedy po raz pierwszy spotkałem Shri Mataji, był tam Gregoire,
of other chappies were there jumping around with me.
wielu innych chłopaków kręciło się razem ze mną.
I remember one, early one morning after we slept with Her in a flat in London, I was
Pamiętam, pewnego wczesnego ranka, po tym jak spaliśmy w Jej mieszkaniu w Londynie,
talking to Her and She says… you see… we were talking about Maya.
rozmawiałem z Nią a Ona powiedziała… widzicie, mówiliśmy o Mayi. I ja powiedziałem:
And I said, “Mother, I wish I could go beyond Maya."
"Matko, pragnę, abym mógł wyjść poza Mayę".
And She said to me, this was some seven or eight years ago, and She said to me, “One
A Ona powiedziała mi, to było siedem czy osiem lat temu, Ona powiedziała mi:
day you will, you will catch me."
"Pewnego dnia Mnie dogonisz".
She said, “You will catch me."
Powiedziała: "Dogonisz Mnie".
And what I’m trying to say, is that this is what we should all aim for.
A to, co próbuję wam powiedzieć to to, do czego wszyscy powinniśmy dążyć.
Try to go beyond that.
Spróbujcie wyjść poza.
And you can only go beyond that when you can touch the feet of the Absolute.
A możecie wyjść poza tylko wtedy, kiedy możecie dotknąć stóp Absolutu.
The Absolute is like a mountain peak which raises above the clouds.
Absolut jest jak górski szczyt, który unosi się nad chmurami.
You cannot rise above the clouds until you rest on that mountain peak.
Nie możecie wznieść się ponad chmury, dopóki nie wesprzecie się na szczycie góry.
So, you cannot rise above Maya, it is impossible until your awareness touches the feet of the
Tak więc nie możecie wznieść się ponad Mayę, to nie jest możliwe, dopóki wasza świadomość nie dotknie stóp Absolutu.
Because above Maya there is nothing but the Absolute, The Atma Tattwa.
Ponieważ ponad Mayą nie ma nic oprócz Absolutu, Atma Tattwa.
You know, the Atma Tattwa rests in the Heart of God the Almighty and ascends to dance in
Wiecie, że Atma Tattwa spoczywa w sercu Boga Wszechmogącego i unosi się, aby tańczyć
the Sahastrara as Sadashiva.
w Sahastrarze jako Sadashiva.
So, the heart is a very important organ.
Więc serce jest bardzo ważnym organem.
Rajabhai said that when Shri Mataji gave him realization, She said, “You young men have
Rajabhai powiedział, że kiedy Shri Mataji dała mu Realizację, powiedziała: "Wy młodzi mężczyźni macie tak twarde serca".
And She was true in the sense.
I nie myliła się.
Most people do have hard hearts.
Większość ludzi
Not necessary their fault.
posiada twarde serca. To nie ich wina.
It may be the result of their experiences in this world.
To może być wynikiem ich doświadczeń na tym świecie. Ale serce
But one’s heart should be like a lotus.
powinno być, jak lotos.
I don’t know how many of you have touched a lotus.
Nie wiem, ilu z was dotykało lotosu.
But the petals are so soft, like silk.
Płatki są tak miękkie, jak jedwab.
The heart of a man should be as soft as that.
Serce człowieka powinno być tak miękkie, jak one.
You see, we have got our realization regardless of everything we have done.
Widzicie, otrzymaliśmy naszą Realizację bez względu na to, co zrobiliśmy.
By the grace of God, the Almighty, by His compassion, profound compassion, profound
Dzięki łasce Boga Wszechmogącego, przez Jego współczucie, głębokie współczucie,
love for mankind, for the children of His Shakti.
głęboką miłość do ludzkości, do dzieci Jego Shakti.
He has granted – He says forget everything, forget it, forget it.
On przyznał - On mówi, zapomnijcie o wszystkim, zapomnijcie o tym, zapomnijcie o tym.
Forgive, you see, I forgive them.
Wybaczcie, widzicie, wybaczam im.
I forgive them.
Wybaczam im.
We have to be the same in our hearts to the rest of the mankind.
Musimy być tacy sami w naszych sercach dla reszty ludzkości.
When the disciples of Christ, Peter I think, once came to Christ and asked them: “How
Kiedy uczeń Chrystusa, myślę, że to był Piotr, przyszedł pewnego dnia do Chrystusa i zapytał:
often should I forgive my brothers, seven times?”
"Jak często powinienem wybaczać moim braciom, siedem razy?"
And He said, “No, seventy times seven."
A On odpowiedział: "Nie, siedemdziesiąt razy siedem".
And what He meant was infinitely.
A to, co miał na myśli, to nieskończenie wiele razy.
You see, one cannot be a good Sahaja Yogi, this is my belief, unless one is kind, and
Widzicie, nie można być dobrym Sahaja yoginem, o tym jestem przekonany,
one is gentle.
dopóki nie jest się życzliwym i nie jest się delikatnym. Życzliwość
Kindness and gentle doesn’t mean weakness.
i delikatność nie oznaczają słabości.
It means being soft, trying to further the other person from one’s heart, caring for
Oznaczają bycie łagodnym, próbując popierać drugą osobę z serca, troszcząc się o to, co Shri Mataji
what Shri Mataji once called in Her lecture, caring for his hita [benevolence].
nazwała w swoim wykładzie, troszcząc się o jej hitę [dobro].
Try to see what is… how to do that which is best for him, how to manipulate him in
Postarajcie się dostrzec, jak zrobić to, co jest dla niej [drugiej osoby] najlepsze, jak nią pokierować
such a way that he raises.
w taki sposób, że ona wzrośnie.
It means, going beyond oneself, you see, when someone is harsh with you, is he harsh with
To znaczy, kiedy ktoś jest wobec was niemiły, wychodząc z siebie, czy jest wobec was niemiły?
If you are Atma how he can be harsh with you?
Jeżeli jesteście Atmą, jak on może być
If you are the Atma you can bear it all.
wobec was niemiły? Jeśli jesteście Atmą możecie znieść to wszystko.
And in spite of that try and resolve.
I pomimo tego próbujcie i rozwiązujcie.
The only thing we cannot really be expected to tolerate is any insult to the Goddess Herself.
Jedyne, czego naprawdę nie można oczekiwać to to, że będziemy tolerować jakąkolwiek zniewagę samej Bogini.
There we have to be strong and firm.
Wtedy musimy być silni i stanowczy.
But it doesn’t mean that we take justice in our own hands.
Ale to nie oznacza, że weźmiemy sprawiedliwość w swoje ręce.
Justice is …, belongs to the Almighty, not to us.
Sprawiedliwość jest... należy do Wszechmogącego, nie do nas. Chrystus powiedział także:
Christ also said, “Judge not that ye be not judged."
"Nie sądźcie, byście nie byli sądzeni".
Made it very clear, that we have no right to judge.
Wyjaśniłem bardzo wyraźnie, że nie mamy prawa osądzać.
We are not going to be sitting there, at the end writing out who should go to hell and
Nie będziemy tam siedzieć, na końcu wypisując, kto powinien pójść do piekła
who should go to heaven.
a kto iść do nieba.
It is going to be done by someone else.
To zrobi ktoś inny.
So, we cannot judge.
Więc nie możemy osądzać.
We have to leave it to God to judge and for us to execute.
Musimy pozostawić Bogu osądzanie, a dla nas wykonywanie.
We cannot abrogate to ourselves any of the qualities of the Almighty, such as justice,
Nie możemy negować żadnych cech Wszechmogącego, takich jak sprawiedliwość,
judgment, decisiveness, planning.
osąd, zdecydowanie, planowanie.
These belong to Him.
To należy do Niego.
We merely execute these.
My tylko to wykonujemy.
But when we are kind to a fellow man, to any living thing that moves, within the context
Ale kiedy jesteśmy dobrzy dla bliźniego, dla każdej żywej istoty, która się porusza, w kontekście
of its dharma on this world, we make the Lord happy.
jej dharmy na tym świecie, uszczęśliwiamy Pana. Nie chcę przez to powiedzieć,
By this I don’t mean that one goes around like jains, not trying to kill insects because
że ktoś krąży jak dźiniści starając się nie zabijać owadów, ponieważ w dharmie
it is in the dharma of the insects to be crushed beneath the feet of man.
owadów jest to, że mają zostać zmiażdżone pod stopami człowieka.
We’ve been both created this way that it has… it is an inevitable outcome of living
Zarówno my jak i one zostaliśmy stworzeni w ten sposób, że ma to… jest to nieunikniony wynik
a normal life.
normalnego życia.
One doesn’t go crazy, you see.
Nie powinniśmy dać się zwariować.
We have to eat.
Musimy jeść.
Chicken, I mean it doesn’t mean you don’t slaughter a chicken to be kind to it.
Kurczaki… chodzi mi o to, nie oznacza to, że nie zabijecie kurczaka, żeby być łaskawym dla niego.
We have to live within the boundaries.
Musimy żyć w granicach zdrowego rozsądku.
But there is no place for unnecessary cruelty in this world.
Ale na tym świecie nie ma miejsca na niepotrzebne okrucieństwo.
The Lord is not cruel.
Pan nie jest okrutny.
And if we are to partake of his essence and of his nature we have to be like Him.
A jeśli mamy brać udział w Jego esencji i Jego naturze, musimy być tacy jak On.
So, the message I’m trying to give you is that in spite of all the splendor that surrounds
Tak więc przesłaniem, które próbuję wam przekazać jest to, że pomimo całej świetności, która otacza
the Goddess and there must be because She is, after all, the Shri Adi Shakti, do not
Boginię i musi być, ponieważ Ona jest w końcu Shri Adi Shakti, nie zapominajcie,
forget that the deepest desire in our heart, the Shuddha Ichha, is to raise you to the
że najgłębszym pragnieniem w naszym sercu, Shuddha Ichha jest wzniesienie was
feet of Her Lord as offerings worthy of Him.
do stóp Jej Pana, jako dary Jego godne.
And in all Her drama She tries constantly in Her movement to bring you to that point.
I w całym swoim dramacie Ona nieustannie próbuje w swoim ruchu doprowadzić was do tego punktu.
And I tell you that there is nothing else in the Universe worth bothering about except
I powiadam wam, że nie ma nic poza tym we Wszechświecie, czym warto się martwić z wyjątkiem tego faktu.
If you love your Mother try to be worthy to be offered by Her to Her Consort.
Jeśli kochacie swoją Matkę postarajcie się być godnymi ofiarowania przez Nią dla Jej Małżonka.
And if you love your Father try to be worthy to be offered to Him.
A jeżeli kochacie swojego Ojca, postarajcie się być godnymi tego, aby być Jemu ofiarowanym.
And if you love Them both this will work out inevitably because Their love will work through
A jeśli kochacie Ich oboje to się nieuchronnie spełni, ponieważ Ich miłość będzie działać
your heart, and the two will mingle, and you cannot help but ascent.
przez wasze serce i Oni będą się łączyć, a wy nie możecie pomóc, ale możecie wznieść się.
Live by your hearts not by your brains.
Żyjcie waszym sercem, nie waszym umysłem.
That is not by your egos and superegos and question the inner desires of your heart.
I nie przez wasze ego i superego, i kwestionowanie wewnętrznych pragnień waszego serca.
Do not question them.
Nie kwestionujcie ich.
You cannot question them.
Nie możecie
They are beyond logic.
ich kwestionować. One są poza logiką.
Live by your heart.
Żyjcie sercem.
If you express your heart you will lead to such a sense of satisfaction with life that
Jeśli wyrazicie swoje serce, doprowadzicie do takiego poczucia zadowolenia z życia,
you cannot be angry with anyone.
że nie będziecie mogli być źli na nikogo.
You will be so happy all the time that it’ll be effortless for your Parents to lift you
Będziecie tak szczęśliwi przez cały czas, że bez wysiłku wasi Rodzice uniosą was
to that level which was your destiny at the moment of your creation.
do poziomu, który był waszym przeznaczeniem w momencie waszego stworzenia.
That is all I have to say.
To wszystko, co miałem do powiedzenia.
Jai Shri Mataji.
Jay Shri Mataji!